The Guide to the Good Fight: the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War: Production Materials ALBA.216
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Good Fight: the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War: Production Materials
1936-1983, (Bulk 1979-1982)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Buchner, Noel
ALBA.216
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Good Fight, a feature-length documentary film released in 1983, pays homage to American volunteers who served with the International Brigades during the Spanish Civil War. The film makes extensive use of archival footage from the war, stills, primary documents, radio broadcasts, newsreels, and interviews. The collection includes research and administrative material created during the production of the project and transcribed interviews with 23 veterans.
Provenance
The Good Fight collection was donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1983 by filmmakers Noel Buchner, Mary Dore and Sam Sills. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Good Fight, a feature-length documentary film released in 1983, pays homage to American volunteers who served with the International Brigades during the Spanish Civil War. The film is an exploration of the political motives that compelled the volunteers to travel to Spain in the 1930s, their weathering of anti-communist sentiment during the 1940s and 50s, and their political engagement in later life. The film makes extensive use of archival footage from the war, stills, primary documents, radio broadcasts, newsreels, and interviews. With the help of an NEH grant, filmmakers Noel Buchner, Mary Dore and Sam Sills interviewed more than 125 combat and medical veterans in the course of researching and editing the film. The final documentary, which is narrated by Studs Terkel, features eleven veterans including Bill Bailey, Steve Nelson, Milt Wolff, Edward Balchowsky, Salaria Kee (a.k.a. Salaria Kea) O’Reilly and Evelyn Hutchins.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Background Files:
This series contains general research and administrative materials created during the production of the project. A copy of the NEH-grant application requesting funding outlines the goals of the project and describes the filmmakers’ approach to the selection of interview candidates and their methodology for conducting filmed oral histories. A file of biographical sketches offers concise profiles on almost 100 volunteers and includes information on family background, wartime experiences, and life after Spain. This series also includes publicity used to promote the film and a sampling of reviews.
Series II, Interview Transcripts:
Includes transcribed interviews of 23 veterans including Bill Bailey, Edward Balchowsky, Ruth Davidow, Benjamin Goldstein, Evelyn Hutchins, Vaughn Love, Steve Nelson, Thomas Page and Milt Wolff. Also includes an interview with producer and actor John Houseman and copy of a memoir by hospital administrator Mildred Rackley Simon.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I: Background Files
II: Interview Transcripts
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Film, photographs and audiotapes from the Good Fight Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library. Inventories of the Good Fight film and audio collections are available.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x African Americans.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Articles.; Biography files.; Correspondence.; Research (document genres).; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Goldstein, Benjamin, 1910-1985; Davidow, Ruth.; Balchowsky, Edward.; Bailey, Bill, 1911-1995; Love, Vaughn; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Simon, Mildred Rackley, 1906-2003; Page, Thomas, 1909-; Wolff, Milton.; Hutchins, Evelyn, 1910-1982.; Houseman, John.; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993
- Series I: Background Files
  - Bessie, Alvah: on L. Hellman and M. Gellhorn, Dec 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bowers, Claude G.: Report and Letters (copies), 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Catholics and Protestants on the Spanish Civil War, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clute, Wilton van: Father's Letter (copy), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Columbia University Research: Einstein, Hull and Ickes Letters, 1936-1938, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cuban Volunteers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Franco and the Franco Regime, undated, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Headline Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Higgins, Jimmy (Canadian Volunteer), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn, undated, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kramer, Jacob (Jake), Jul 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lossowski, Vincent, undated, 1944-1945, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Maki, Martin, undated, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Malbin, Virginia, Feb 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Marzani, Carl, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - McKay, Virginia: "A Refugee from Red Spain", 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miami, FL: Anti-Communist Investigations, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Muller, Herman J., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Namuth, Hans and Georg Reisner: "Photographs from the Spanish Civil War", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grant Proposal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nelson, Steve, undated, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pappas, Nick: Interview on the Spanish Civil War, Oct 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Publicity, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Return of Project Materials, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Robinson, Edward (Frenchie), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Soundtrack: Notes and Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Stowe, Leland: "Part of the War Isn't News", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - United States Relations with Spain, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Veterans: Biographical Sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Dellums Bill on Veterans Benefits, Jan 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: General, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Veterans: Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Veterans: Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Weissman, Irving, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Welles, Orson, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Wolff, Milton, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series II: Interview Transcripts
  - Alexander, Frank, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bailey, Bill (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bailey, Bill (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Balchowsky, Edward, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Brier, Morris, Sep 1981 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Chisholm, Albert, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Davidow, Ruth, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Goldstein, Benjamin (Butch), undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Hollander, Fay and Hy, Jan 1980 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Holtzman, Benjamin, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Houseman, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Love, Vaughn, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Matthews, William, Jun 1980 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - McCarthy, Bill, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Nelson, Steve, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Osheroff, Abe, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Page, Thomas (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Page, Thomas (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Peck, Sam, Jan 1980 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Rackley (Simon), Mildred: Memoir, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Rody, John, Jul 1980 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Roosevelt, Patrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Smith, Randall B. (Pete), undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Taylor, Robert, Jun 1980 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Thompson, Dave, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Wolff, Milton (I), undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Wolff, Milton (II), undated (Box 1, Folder 66)